All right, welcome everybody.
자, 모두 환영합니다.
So today I want to talk about one of the newer projects going on in OpenJDK.
오늘은 OpenJDK에서 진행 중인 새로운 프로젝트 중 하나에 대해 이야기하고 싶습니다.
At the keynote this morning, you know, I showed a long list of projects, Loom, Panama, Valhalla,
오늘 아침 기조연설에서 Loom, Panama, Valhalla 등 많은 프로젝트 목록을 보여드렸습니다,
Babylon.
바빌론.
And Leiden is one of the newer projects we started working on it maybe six months ago
라이덴은 약 6개월 전에 시작한 새로운 프로젝트 중 하나입니다.
or so, which is aimed at improving startup and warm-up of Java applications.
정도이며, Java 애플리케이션의 시작 및 워밍업을 개선하는 데 목적이 있습니다.
So to define our terms a little bit, what is startup and what is warm-up?
용어를 조금 정의하자면, 스타트업과 웜업이란 무엇일까요?
Startup is the amount of time it takes to get to the first useful unit of work.
시작은 첫 번째 유용한 작업 단위에 도달하는 데 걸리는 시간입니다.
Warm-up is the time it takes for an application to reach peak performance.
워밍업은 애플리케이션이 최고 성능에 도달하는 데 걸리는 시간입니다.
So both of these things include a mix of activities, both work that is done by an application
따라서 이 두 가지 모두 애플리케이션이 수행하는 여러 가지 작업이 혼합되어 있습니다.
and work that is done on behalf of an application.
그리고 애플리케이션을 대신하여 수행되는 작업.
So if you have a typical server application, when it starts up, it's going to go through
따라서 일반적인 서버 애플리케이션이 있다면, 애플리케이션이 시작될 때 다음과 같은 과정을 거치게 됩니다.
the usual parse the configuration file, open some sockets, create listeners, create loggers,
구성 파일을 파싱하고, 소켓을 열고, 리스너를 생성하고, 로거를 생성하는 일반적인 과정을 거칩니다,
create more loggers, create a lot of loggers.
더 많은 로거를 생성하고, 많은 로거를 생성합니다.
And that is work that is done by the application.
그리고 이것은 애플리케이션이 하는 일입니다.
At the same time, the JVM is doing work on behalf of the application.
동시에 JVM은 애플리케이션을 대신하여 작업을 수행하고 있습니다.
It's loading classes, it's validating class files, it's jitting classes, it's resolving
클래스를 로드하고, 클래스 파일의 유효성을 검사하고, 클래스를 지팅하고, 해결하고 있습니다.
constant pool entries, it's symbolically linking call sites, things like that.
상수 풀 항목, 호출 사이트 등을 상징적으로 연결하고 있습니다.
And startup and warm-up are an issue for some Java applications, not for all.
그리고 시작 및 워밍업은 일부 Java 애플리케이션의 문제이지 모든 애플리케이션의 문제는 아닙니다.
I want to talk first a little bit about where these issues come from, if they are issues,
먼저 이러한 문제가 발생하는 원인에 대해 조금 이야기하고 싶습니다,
and then what we're doing to offer a range of choices to make it better.
그리고 이를 개선하기 위해 다양한 선택지를 제공하기 위해 우리가 무엇을 하고 있는지에 대해 이야기하고 싶습니다.
The main reason why startup and warm-up are an issue for Java applications is because
Java 애플리케이션에서 시작 및 워밍업이 문제가 되는 주된 이유는 다음과 같습니다.
of Java's dynamism.
자바의 역동성 때문입니다.
And some of you are thinking, probably, wait a second, I thought Java was a static language.
잠깐만요, 자바는 정적인 언어인 줄 알았는데요, 라고 생각하시는 분들도 계실 겁니다.
So I want to talk about the terms static and dynamic because they're frequently misused
그래서 정적과 동적이라는 용어가 자주 오용되기 때문에 이 용어에 대해 이야기하고 싶습니다.
and abused.
남용되고 있습니다.
And they mean a lot of different things in different contexts.
이 단어들은 서로 다른 맥락에서 다양한 의미를 지니고 있습니다.
So I'm going to start with a very simplistic notion of static versus dynamic, which is
그래서 저는 정적과 동적에 대한 아주 단순한 개념으로 시작하겠습니다.
wrong but we'll get to something better, where let's assume that static means at compile
잘못되었지만 더 나은 것을 얻게 될 것입니다, 여기서 정적은 컴파일 시점에
time and dynamic means at runtime.
시간, 동적은 런타임을 의미한다고 가정해봅시다.
Like I said, not a good starting assumption, but we have to start somewhere.
앞서 말했듯이 좋은 출발점은 아니지만 어디선가 시작해야 합니다.
So the question I would ask is, is Java statically typed or dynamically typed?
제가 묻고 싶은 질문은 자바가 정적 타입인가, 동적 타입인가 하는 것입니다.
The answer is yes.
정답은 '예'입니다.
The answer is Java is both statically typed and dynamically typed.
정답은 Java는 정적 타입과 동적 타입 모두입니다.
So Java has a static type system that's enforced by the compiler, and it has various rules
따라서 Java에는 컴파일러에 의해 강제되는 정적 유형 시스템이 있으며 다양한 규칙이 있습니다.
about conversion and overload selection and such.
변환과 과부하 선택 등에 관한 규칙이 있습니다.
Java also has a dynamic type system, which is enforced at runtime by the JVM.
Java에는 런타임에 JVM에 의해 강제 적용되는 동적 유형 시스템도 있습니다.
The two have a lot in common in both the static and dynamic type systems.
정적 타입 시스템과 동적 타입 시스템 모두 공통점이 많습니다.
String is a subtype of object, but they also have significant differences.
문자열은 객체의 하위 유형이지만 상당한 차이점도 있습니다.
And it's not that one is a pure subset of the other, although in general the dynamic
그리고 일반적으로 둘 중 하나가 다른 하나의 순수한 하위 집합은 아니지만, 일반적으로 동적인
type system tends to be weaker than the static type system.
타입 시스템은 정적 타입 시스템보다 약한 경향이 있습니다.
And that's true across a lot of languages.
이는 많은 언어에서 마찬가지입니다.
But for example, some things that are part of the static type system that are not part
하지만 예를 들어 정적 타입 시스템의 일부이지만 일부가 아닌 것들도 있습니다.
of the dynamic type system are things like generics.
동적 타입 시스템의 일부가 아닌 것들은 제네릭과 같은 것들입니다.
We type check generics at compile time, and then we erase them away.
컴파일 시 제네릭을 타입 검사한 다음 지워버립니다.
The check-ed-ness of exceptions also happens to be something erased away at compilation
예외를 검사하는 것도 컴파일 시에 지워집니다.
time.
시간.
Not everybody's aware of that.
모두가 알고 있는 것은 아닙니다.
Definite assignment analysis is part of the static type system.
정적 할당 분석은 정적 유형 시스템의 일부입니다.
So Java requires that you initialize a local variable before you use it.
따라서 Java에서는 지역 변수를 사용하기 전에 반드시 초기화해야 합니다.
The JVM doesn't enforce that, but the compiler does.
JVM은 이를 강제하지 않지만 컴파일러는 강제합니다.
Overload resolution is another of what we call language fictions, which is checked at
과부하 해결은 우리가 언어의 허구라고 부르는 또 다른 문제이며, 다음에서 확인됩니다.
compile time and then ignored thereafter.
컴파일 시간에 검사되고 그 이후에는 무시됩니다.
On the other hand, there are aspects of the dynamic type system that are not part of the
반면에, 동적 타입 시스템에서는
static type system.
정적 유형 시스템.
The best example of that is array store exception.
가장 좋은 예는 배열 저장소 예외입니다.
So if I have an array that is an object array, and I go to store a string in it using the
예를 들어 객체 배열인 배열이 있고 그 배열에 문자열을 저장하려고 하면
ASTORE bytecode, I may get an array store exception.
ASTORE 바이트코드를 사용하면 배열 저장소 예외가 발생할 수 있습니다.
And the reason is that object array might actually be an array of integers.
그 이유는 객체 배열이 실제로 정수의 배열일 수 있기 때문입니다.
It may be an integer array because arrays are covariant in Java.
자바에서 배열은 공변량이기 때문에 정수 배열일 수 있습니다.
So I can cast an integer array to an object array, and then if I try to put a string into
따라서 정수 배열을 객체 배열로 형변환한 다음 문자열을 넣으려고 하면
the array, the runtime will say, no, you can't do that.
배열에 문자열을 넣으려고 하면 런타임이 '안 됩니다'라고 말합니다.
So this is all a long-winded way of saying that even the simplistic notion of static
이 모든 것은 정적이라는 단순한 개념조차도 장황하게 설명한 것입니다.
and dynamic are about compile time versus runtime, and that static and dynamic are only
와 동적은 컴파일 시간 대 런타임에 관한 것이고, 정적과 동적은 단지
about typing, even with these simplistic assumptions, Java doesn't fit neatly into a category of
이러한 단순한 가정에도 불구하고, 자바는 다음과 같은 범주에 깔끔하게 들어맞지 않습니다.
static or dynamic.
정적 또는 동적.
So let's backpedal on some of these assumptions.
이제 몇 가지 가정을 다시 살펴봅시다.
Now whenever you get confused about the meaning of terms, it's always a good idea to look
이제 용어의 의미가 헷갈릴 때마다 항상 다음을 살펴보는 것이 좋습니다.
in the dictionary.
를 사전에서 찾아보세요.
So if you look up static and dynamic, for static you get a lot of words about at rest,
정적과 동적을 찾아보면, 정적의 경우 정지 상태에 대한 단어가 많이 나옵니다,
without motion, in equilibrium, showing little change.
움직임이 없고, 평형 상태이며, 변화가 거의 없습니다.
For dynamic, you see a lot of definitions that talk about marked by change, marked by
동적의 경우, 다음과 같이 변화로 표시되는 것에 대해 이야기하는 많은 정의를 볼 수 있습니다.
a productive activity, energetic, forceful, changing, et cetera.
생산적인 활동, 활기찬, 힘찬, 변화하는 등등.
So we sort of have a general idea here that the distinction between static and dynamic
그래서 우리는 정적인 것과 동적인 것을 구분하는 일반적인 아이디어를 가지고 있습니다.
is changing versus unchanging.
는 변화하는 것과 변하지 않는 것입니다.
So let's run with that.
그럼 실행해 봅시다.
And there's a couple of aspects here that we want to tease apart.
여기서 몇 가지 살펴보고 싶은 부분이 있습니다.
One is, well, what is actually changing?
하나는, 실제로 무엇이 바뀌고 있는가?
And in the context when we talk about languages being static or dynamic, we tend to think
그리고 언어가 정적인지 동적인지에 대해 이야기할 때, 우리는 다음과 같이 생각하는 경향이 있습니다.
of this strictly in terms of typing.
엄격하게 타이핑의 관점에서만 생각하는 경향이 있습니다.
Java is statically typed, Python is dynamically typed.
자바는 정적 타입이고, 파이썬은 동적 타입입니다.
But in fact, there are many, many other axes of static versus dynamic that languages and
하지만 사실 정적 대 동적의 다른 많은 축이 있으며 언어와
runtimes might engage in.
런타임이 관여할 수 있습니다.
So for example, Java has, as I just talked about, dynamic typing.
예를 들어 Java에는 방금 말씀드린 것처럼 동적 타이핑이 있습니다.
It also has dynamic class loading, dynamic class verification, dynamic class redefinition,
또한 동적 클래스 로딩, 동적 클래스 검증, 동적 클래스 재정의도 있습니다,
dynamic compilation, which we call JIT compilation, dynamic recompilation, which we call deoptimization.
동적 컴파일(JIT 컴파일), 동적 재컴파일(디옵티마이제이션)이 있습니다.
This is where we may have JIT compiled a class, and then for whatever reason, the VM decides,
이 시점에서 JIT 컴파일을 통해 클래스를 컴파일한 후 어떤 이유로든 VM이 결정할 수 있습니다,
I don't like that compilation.
컴파일이 마음에 들지 않습니다.
I want to throw it away and change it.
버리고 바꾸고 싶어요.
So what happens is we evict the compiled code from the code cache, go back to the interpreter,
그래서 컴파일된 코드를 코드 캐시에서 내보내고 인터프리터로 돌아갑니다,
and maybe recompile later.
그리고 나중에 다시 컴파일합니다.
Call sites and field accesses in Java are dynamically linked.
Java에서 호출 사이트와 필드 액세스가 동적으로 연결됩니다.
What that means is the first time client code calls a method in another class, there's a
즉, 클라이언트 코드가 다른 클래스의 메서드를 처음 호출할 때
bunch of activity for, OK, what method are you actually calling?
에 대한 많은 활동이 발생하는데, 실제로 어떤 메서드를 호출하는 걸까요?
And this involves comparing strings for field and method descriptors.
여기에는 필드와 메서드 설명자에 대한 문자열 비교가 포함됩니다.
It only happens on the first call thereafter.
이후 첫 번째 호출에서만 발생합니다.
The linkage information is cached, so it's not as slow as it sounds.
연결 정보가 캐시되어 있기 때문에 생각보다 느리지 않습니다.
But we do linkage dynamically, and that is what enables us to take a jar and drop a new
하지만 우리는 동적으로 연결하기 때문에 항아리를 가져다가 새로운
jar onto the class path and have everything just work.
jar를 클래스 경로에 놓으면 모든 것이 정상적으로 작동합니다.
Java has dynamic dispatch through virtual methods.
Java에는 가상 메서드를 통한 동적 디스패치가 있습니다.
It has dynamic introspection through reflection and features like instance of and casting.
리플렉션을 통한 동적 성찰과 인스턴스 및 캐스팅과 같은 기능이 있습니다.
So even though we'd like to think that Java is a mostly static language, Java is actually
따라서 자바가 대부분 정적인 언어라고 생각하고 싶지만, 사실 자바는
really dynamic.
정말 동적입니다.
So one dimension of static versus dynamic is what is changing and what is not changing.
정적인 것과 동적인 것의 한 차원은 변화하는 것과 변화하지 않는 것입니다.
The other dimension is when is it changing?
또 다른 차원은 언제 변하는가입니다.
Over what period is it changing or not changing?
어느 기간 동안 변화하거나 변화하지 않는가?
So earlier I described the sort of naive division of compile time versus runtime, which is usually
앞서 컴파일 시간과 런타임의 순진한 구분을 설명했는데, 보통은 다음과 같습니다.
the thing that comes to mind when we talk about something being done statically or something
정적으로 수행되는 무언가에 대해 이야기할 때 떠오르는 것들입니다.
done dynamically.
동적으로 수행됩니다.
But in reality, there are many, many interesting phase transitions in a program where something
하지만 실제로 프로그램에는 흥미로운 위상 전환이 아주 많이 존재합니다.
that happens before a phase transition and is held constant throughout the next phase
위상 전이 전에 발생하고 다음 위상 내내 일정하게 유지됩니다.
is called static, even though it was dynamic in the previous phase.
이전 단계에서는 동적이었더라도 정적이라고 합니다.
And as an example of that, take a line of code like this, where we say static final
그 예로, 정적 최종이라고 하는 다음과 같은 코드 줄을 살펴봅시다.
int seed equals, and then we go off to the hardware randomness source and we ask it for
int 시드 같다고 한 다음, 하드웨어 임의성 소스로 가서
a random number.
난수를 요청합니다.
So is that static or dynamic?
정적인가, 아니면 동적인가?
Well, duh, it says static right there, right?
저기 정적이라고 되어 있잖아요?
Well, so that's part of the story.
그게 이야기의 일부군요.
But when does that initializer run, the get random number?
하지만 그 이니셜라이저는 언제 실행될까요, 난수 추출은?
That runs at runtime.
런타임에 실행됩니다.
That sounds pretty dynamic to me.
꽤 역동적으로 들리네요.
On the other hand, the value of that seed is held constant for the entirety of its visible
반면에, 해당 시드의 값은 보이는 전체 기간 동안 일정하게 유지됩니다.
lifetime.
수명 동안 일정하게 유지됩니다.
So no one can ever see it change.
그래서 아무도 변하는 것을 볼 수 없습니다.
Well, unchanging.
음, 변하지 않네요.
That sounds kind of static.
좀 정적이네요.
But on the other, other, other hand, this lifetime doesn't coincide with the sort of
하지만 다른 한편으로, 다른 한편으로, 이 수명은 일치하지 않습니다.
compile time versus runtime distinction.
컴파일 시간과 런타임을 구분합니다.
So it kind of gives you an idea that we're used to playing very fast and loose with these
이를 통해 우리가 매우 빠르고 느슨하게 플레이하는 데 익숙하다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
terms and that can often get us in trouble.
종종 곤경에 처할 수 있습니다.
So one of the things that the JVM is very good at is optimizing things that were born
따라서 JVM이 매우 잘하는 것 중 하나는 이미 만들어진 것을 최적화하는 것입니다.
dynamic as if they were static.
동적인 것을 마치 정적인 것처럼 최적화하는 것입니다.
So for example, the static final field example, what the JVM is going to do is it is going
예를 들어, 정적 최종 필드 예제에서 JVM이 수행하는 작업은 다음과 같습니다.
to aggressively inline that as a constant into things like generated code and constant
을 생성된 코드와 상수 같은 것에 상수로 적극적으로 인라인하는 것입니다.
folding, constant propagation and all of that, even though there's a real element of dynamism
폴딩, 상수 전파 등 실제 동적 요소가 있음에도 불구하고 말이죠.
going on here.
계속 진행 중입니다.
And this is really part of the JVM philosophy that there is this yin and yang of static
이것은 정적과 동적의 음과 양이 존재한다는 JVM 철학의 일부입니다.
versus dynamic that is not a contradiction.
모순이 아닌 동적이라는 음과 양이 있습니다.
It's a strength.
강점입니다.
Rather than choosing static versus dynamic, the Java answers almost always both please.
정적과 동적 중 하나를 선택하기보다는 자바는 거의 항상 두 가지 모두 만족스럽게 대답합니다.
And so we consider it a core JVM competency to optimize calculations that may look static
따라서 정적으로 보일 수 있는 계산을 최적화하는 것이 JVM의 핵심 역량이라고 생각합니다.
for a certain period of time even though they were dynamic in an earlier phase.
이전 단계에서는 동적이었더라도 일정 기간 동안은 정적으로 보일 수 있습니다.
And that includes things like the field initialization example that I just showed.
여기에는 방금 보여드린 필드 초기화 예제 같은 것들이 포함됩니다.
And it also includes things like class loading, which is done dynamically and lazily.
또한 동적이고 느리게 수행되는 클래스 로딩과 같은 것들도 포함됩니다.
And lots and lots of JIT optimizations take advantage of that.
그리고 수많은 JIT 최적화가 이를 활용합니다.
Another thing JVMs like to do and are very good at is hiding the evidence when it guesses
JVM이 좋아하고 매우 잘하는 또 다른 일은 추측할 때 증거를 숨기는 것입니다.
wrong.
틀렸다.
So one of the coolest optimizations that JVMs do routinely is class hierarchy based speculative
JVM이 일상적으로 수행하는 가장 멋진 최적화 중 하나는 클래스 계층 구조 기반의 추측성 최적화입니다.
optimization of polymorphic call sites.
다형성 호출 사이트의 최적화입니다.
And what that means is when you go to call a method that's defined, say, in an interface,
이는 예를 들어 인터페이스에 정의된 메서드를 호출할 때를 의미합니다,
ordinarily you would think, oh, that has to be a virtual call.
보통은 가상 호출이어야 한다고 생각할 것입니다.
And you have some idea of what the mechanics of a virtual call is with looking things up
그리고 가상 통화의 메커니즘에 대해 어느 정도는 알고 있습니다.
in VTables and things like that.
같은 것들에서요.
But the JVM is entirely free to say, I happen to know that there's only one implementation
하지만 JVM은 전적으로 자유롭게 말할 수 있으며, 제가 알기로는 구현이 하나뿐인 것으로 알고 있습니다.
of that interface loaded.
가 로드되었습니다.
So I know exactly where this call is going.
그래서 저는 이 호출이 어디로 가는지 정확히 알고 있습니다.
And I'm not going to go through the VTable.
그리고 난 VTable을 통과하지 않을 거야.
I'm going to do a direct call.
직접 전화를 걸겠습니다.
In fact, I'm going to inline through it.
사실, 인라인으로 통과하겠습니다.
And this is something that the VM does.
그리고 이것은 VM이 하는 일입니다.
But it's kind of a dodgy thing to do because a minute later I can load another class that
하지만 1분 후에 다른 클래스를 로드할 수 있기 때문에 이는 다소 애매한 작업입니다.
violates that assumption and invalidates the optimization that I just described.
이 가정을 위반하고 방금 설명한 최적화를 무효화하기 때문입니다.
Not a problem.
문제 없습니다.
It's the same JVM that's doing the class loading that's doing the JITing.
클래스 로딩을 수행하는 JVM이 JIT를 수행하는 것과 동일합니다.
So when you go to load something that would violate a previous assumption, it says, wait
따라서 이전 가정을 위반할 수 있는 무언가를 로드하려고 하면 다음과 같이 표시됩니다.
a second, hold off on this class loading for a minute.
이 클래스 로딩을 1분간 보류합니다.
Let me go evict some code from the code cache because it has bad assumptions now.
코드 캐시에 잘못된 가정이 있으므로 코드 캐시에서 일부 코드를 제거하겠습니다.
That will fall back to interpretation and get reoptimized later.
나중에 다시 해석해서 다시 최적화하겠습니다.
And then I'll continue with the class loading.
그리고 나서 클래스 로딩을 계속하겠습니다.
So this is an example of something that is dynamic.
이것이 동적인 것의 예시입니다.
But if you squint, it might be static for long enough that it's worth trying to optimize
하지만 눈을 가늘게 뜨면 충분히 오랫동안 정적일 수 있으므로 최적화를 시도할 가치가 있습니다.
something.
뭔가.
And if you're wrong, the VM is able to recover without exposing a failure.
그리고 잘못 입력한 경우에도 장애를 노출하지 않고 VM이 복구할 수 있습니다.
So this is something that VMs do all the time.
이 작업은 VM이 항상 수행하는 작업입니다.
We don't even notice it.
우리는 눈치채지 못합니다.
It's a wonderful thing.
멋진 일이야.
This is why Java can often outperform C because it's allowed to make optimizations that are
이것이 바로 Java가 종종 C보다 성능이 뛰어난 이유입니다.
not provably true as long as we will know when they become invalidated.
언제 무효화되는지 알 수 있는 한 증명할 수 없는 사실입니다.
Similarly, we may want to deoptimize on the basis of we gather profile information, compile
마찬가지로, 우리는 프로필 정보를 수집하고, 컴파일하여
code in a certain way, then we gather more profile information and decide, you know what?
코드를 컴파일한 다음, 더 많은 프로필 정보를 수집하고 결정할 수 있습니다.
That was a bad compilation.
컴파일이 잘못됐어.
I can imagine a better compilation.
더 나은 컴파일을 상상할 수 있어요.
I'm going to kick that code out of the code cache and recompile it.
코드 캐시에서 해당 코드를 걷어내고 다시 컴파일하겠습니다.
So this is like business as usual in the JVM, is balancing this static and dynamic reasoning.
정적 추론과 동적 추론의 균형을 맞추는 것은 JVM의 일반적인 업무와 같습니다.
OK.
알겠습니다.
So none of this has anything to do with startup, right?
이 모든 것이 시작과 관련이 없는 거죠?
Well, let's talk about what happens at startup.
그럼 스타트 업에서 일어나는 일에 대해 이야기해 봅시다.
So when a program starts up, like I said, there are activities that might be part of
프로그램이 시작되면, 제가 말씀드린 것처럼, 다음과 같은 활동이 있을 수 있습니다.
your program or your framework or libraries that you use, like reading configuration files
구성 파일 읽기 같은 프로그램이나 프레임워크, 사용하는 라이브러리의 일부일 수 있습니다.
or scanning for annotations, opening sockets, creating loggers, like I said, and also class
또는 주석 검색, 소켓 열기, 로거 생성, 내가 말했던 것처럼 클래스
loading, class verification, class file metadata construction, static initializers, interpretation,
로딩, 클래스 검증, 클래스 파일 메타데이터 구성, 정적 이니셜라이저, 해석,
profile gathering, call site linkage, all of these things happen at startup.
프로필 수집, 통화 사이트 연결, 이 모든 것이 시작과 동시에 이루어집니다.
And similarly, at warmup, warmup sort of extends over a longer period of time than startup,
마찬가지로 워밍업 단계에서는 시작보다 더 오랜 시간 동안 워밍업이 진행됩니다,
we see the same split of there are activities that are part of the program that govern warmup,
워밍업을 관장하는 프로그램의 일부인 활동이 동일하게 분할되는 것을 볼 수 있습니다,
like populating caches, and there are JVM activities, like JIT compilation of hot code
캐시 채우기와 같은 프로그램이 있고, 핫 코드의 JIT 컴파일과 같은 JVM 활동이 있습니다.
that affect warmup.
워밍업에 영향을 줍니다.
OK.
So million dollar question, why do we do it this way?
백만 달러짜리 질문인데, 왜 이런 식으로 하는 거죠?
At first, it sounds really inefficient to do what I just described, to do all of that
처음에는 방금 설명한 대로 모든 작업을 수행하는 것이 정말 비효율적으로 들립니다.
work every time the program starts.
프로그램이 시작될 때마다 작업합니다.
Are you crazy?
미쳤어?
And the reason is dynamism benefits both the programming model and the performance model.
그 이유는 역동성이 프로그래밍 모델과 성능 모델 모두에 도움이 되기 때문입니다.
So dynamic features like on the fly class loading and reflection make Java programs
따라서 온 더 플라이 클래스 로딩 및 리플렉션과 같은 동적 기능은 Java 프로그램에서
more expressive.
더 표현력이 풍부해집니다.
The frameworks that we use every day would be much harder to write if we didn't have
우리가 매일 사용하는 프레임워크는 다음과 같은 기능이 없었다면 작성하기가 훨씬 더 어려웠을 것입니다.
reflection, if we didn't have annotations, if we didn't have dynamic class loading.
리플렉션이 없다면, 어노테이션이 없다면, 동적 클래스 로딩이 없다면, 우리가 매일 사용하는 프레임워크를 작성하기가 훨씬 더 어려웠을 것입니다.
Similarly, dynamic compilation, JIT compilation, generally produces better code than static
마찬가지로, 동적 컴파일인 JIT 컴파일은 일반적으로 정적 컴파일보다 더 나은 코드를 생성합니다.
compilation for the very obvious reason that if you're compiling at runtime, you have more
컴파일보다 더 나은 코드를 생성하는데, 그 이유는 런타임에 컴파일하는 경우 더 많은
information than if you were compiling at build time.
더 많은 정보를 얻을 수 있기 때문입니다.
You have information about the hardware you're actually running on, not just the abstract
추상적인 정보뿐만 아니라 실제로 실행 중인 하드웨어에 대한 정보도 얻을 수 있습니다.
Intel instruction set.
인텔 명령어 세트.
You have information about that was gathered during profiling of what has the program actually
프로그램이 실제로 무엇을 가지고 있는지에 대한 프로파일링 중에 수집된 정보가 있습니다.
done, has this branch actually been taken, has a null ever shown up at this dispatch
완료되었는지, 이 분기를 실제로 가져갔는지, 이 디스패치에 널이 나타난 적이 있는지?
site, et cetera.
사이트 등
And so we can use that information to produce better code.
그리고 그 정보를 이용해 더 나은 코드를 만들 수 있습니다.
And then if it turns out that we gather more data and our opinions change about what would
그리고 더 많은 데이터를 수집하고 의견이 바뀐다면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
constitute a good optimization, we can de-optimize and re-optimize.
최적화를 해제하고 다시 최적화할 수 있습니다.
And we can do that based on observed program behavior.
그리고 관찰된 프로그램 동작을 기반으로 그렇게 할 수 있습니다.
So all of this dynamism makes for a good user programming model and excellent peak
이 모든 역동성이 좋은 사용자 프로그래밍 모델과 우수한 피크를 만들어냅니다.
performance.
성능.
So what's the cost?
그럼 비용은 얼마인가요?
Everything's a trade-off.
모든 건 장단점이 있죠.
The cost of that is slower startup and warm-up.
그 대가는 느린 시작과 워밍업입니다.
For some applications, like think about a WebLogic server which starts up and runs for
일부 애플리케이션의 경우, 예를 들어 시작 및 실행되는 웹로직 서버를 생각해보십시오.
months, this is an excellent trade-off.
개월 동안 실행되는 서버를 생각해보면, 이것은 훌륭한 절충안입니다.
The fact that it takes a while to start up may not be an issue.
시작하는 데 시간이 걸린다는 사실은 문제가 되지 않을 수 있습니다.
And the fact that you get better peak performance is definitely a good thing.
그리고 최고 성능이 향상된다는 사실은 확실히 좋은 일입니다.
On the other hand, if you have something like a command line application, the user is waiting
반면에, 명령줄 애플리케이션과 같은 것이 있다면 사용자는
to see feedback, they may care more about startup and they probably don't care about
피드백을 보기 위해, 시작에 더 신경을 쓸 수 있고 아마도
peak performance because your short-running command line application probably doesn't
단기 실행 명령줄 응용 프로그램은 아마도 그렇지 않을 것이기 때문에 최고 성능
even get out of the interpreter.
심지어 인터프리터에서 빠져나올 수도 있습니다.
So all of this is to say that different workloads have different requirements and we want Java
이 모든 것은 워크로드마다 요구사항이 다르고, 우리는 자바가
to be good for all of them.
가 모든 워크로드에 적합하기를 바랍니다.
So to sort of visualize startup and warm-up, imagine there's an ideal behavior, which is
따라서 시작과 워밍업을 시각화하기 위해 다음과 같은 이상적인 동작이 있다고 상상해 보세요.
by this green line at the bottom here, where this is the amount of time it takes to do
여기 하단의 녹색 선은 이 작업을 수행하는 데 걸리는 시간입니다.
each task in a program that does repetitive tasks, which a lot of programs do.
반복적인 작업을 수행하는 프로그램에서 각 작업을 수행하는 데 걸리는 시간입니다.
Some programs just do one thing and exit.
어떤 프로그램은 한 가지 일만 하고 종료합니다.
And you can see that the timeline for the first task is going to be higher than for
그리고 첫 번째 작업의 타임라인이 다음 작업보다 더 길어지는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
subsequent tasks because we do more work before the first task than we do before the second
두 번째 작업보다 첫 번째 작업 전에 더 많은 작업을 수행하기 때문입니다.
task.
작업.
Now, most programs end up with something more like the yellow line, where you have the same
이제 대부분의 프로그램은 노란색 선과 비슷한 형태로 끝납니다.
qualitative shape, but the reality is that there's a big head on startup.
질적인 모양을 가지고 있지만, 현실은 시작에 큰 머리가 있다는 것입니다.
And then there is a gradual convergence between the observed performance and the ideal performance.
그리고 관찰된 성능과 이상적인 성능 사이에 점진적인 수렴이 일어납니다.
So the work under this first unit of time is startup activity, and typically that's
따라서 이 첫 번째 시간 단위의 작업은 시작 활동이며, 일반적으로 다음과 같습니다.
driven by things like class loading, class initialization, which are unique to the first
클래스 로딩, 클래스 초기화 같은 것들에 의해 구동됩니다.
iteration.
이터레이션.
And the stuff that is below the other line is generally online JIT activity for identifying
그리고 다른 줄 아래에 있는 항목은 일반적으로 식별을 위한 온라인 JIT 활동입니다.
hot classes, compiling hot classes, and it's going to take a certain amount of time for
핫 클래스, 핫 클래스 컴파일, 그리고 일정 시간이 걸릴 것입니다.
the hot code to all be compiled, which is what warm-up basically means.
핫 코드가 모두 컴파일되는 데 일정 시간이 걸리는데, 이것이 바로 워밍업의 기본 의미입니다.
So startup tends to be a very short-lived thing.
따라서 시작은 매우 짧게 끝나는 경향이 있습니다.
Warm-up tends to be a longer-lived thing.
워밍업은 더 오래 지속되는 경향이 있습니다.
So if we want to improve startup and warm-up, what do we have to do?
그렇다면 스타트와 워밍업을 개선하려면 어떻게 해야 할까요?
Well we have to find a way to push the first point down if we're looking to optimize startup
시작을 최적화하려면 첫 번째 지점을 낮추는 방법을 찾아야 합니다.
and to push the whole curve down if we're looking to optimize warm-up.
워밍업을 최적화하려면 전체 곡선을 아래로 밀어내야 합니다.
Okay, so how do we push these curves down?
그럼 이 커브를 어떻게 아래로 내릴까요?
Well we need to move work off the critical path.
작업을 임계 경로에서 벗어나야 합니다.
That might mean moving it later in time, like being lazy about things, not creating loggers
그건 일을 게으르게 처리하고 로거를 만들지 않는 것처럼 나중에 옮기는 것을 의미할 수 있습니다.
that we don't need to create immediately.
당장 만들 필요가 없는 것들.
Or we could shift work earlier in time, from runtime to build time or deploy time or packaging
또는 런타임에서 빌드 시간이나 배포 시간 또는 패키징 시간으로 작업을 앞당길 수도 있습니다.
time or some earlier phase of execution where we're going to run some Java code and remember
시간 또는 자바 코드를 실행하는 초기 실행 단계로 작업을 옮길 수 있습니다.
the answer.
을 기억합니다.
And we can shift work, both of these categories of work, work that's part of the application,
그리고 우리는 이 두 가지 범주의 작업, 즉 애플리케이션의 일부인 작업을 교대 근무로 전환할 수 있습니다,
as well as shifting work on behalf of the application.
애플리케이션을 대신하여 작업을 이동시킬 수도 있습니다.
And this is sort of old hat for what JVMs do.
그리고 이것은 JVM이 하는 일에 대해 일종의 오래된 방식입니다.
JVM already employs a lot of computation shifting techniques, such as garbage collection and
JVM은 이미 가비지 컬렉션과 같은 많은 연산 이동 기법을 사용하고 있습니다.
constant folding and lazy class loading, etc.
상수 폴딩과 지연 클래스 로딩 등 많은 연산 이동 기법을 사용하고 있습니다.
So a lot of these optimizations just fall out of the normal semantics of Java programs.
따라서 이러한 최적화의 대부분은 자바 프로그램의 일반적인 의미론에서 벗어난 것입니다.
So if you have an arithmetic expression, x equals 2 plus 3, well we could push a 2 and
예를 들어, x가 2 더하기 3과 같은 산술식이 있다면, 우리는 2를 밀어넣고
a 3 on the stack at runtime and add them, or we could do the computation at compile
를 런타임에 스택에 밀어넣고 더하거나, 컴파일할 때 계산을 할 수도 있습니다.
time.
시간.
And the language specification allows us to do either, because it just tells us what answer
그리고 언어 명세는 어떤 답을 알려주기 때문에 어느 쪽이든 할 수 있습니다.
we're supposed to get.
얻을 수 있습니다.
It doesn't tell us how efficiently we're supposed to do it.
얼마나 효율적으로 해야 하는지는 알려주지 않습니다.
So there are a lot of optimizations that we can do where the specification is agnostic
따라서 사양에 구애받지 않고 할 수 있는 최적화가 많이 있습니다.
on what we're doing.
우리가 하는 일에 대해.
Similarly, garbage collection, the timing of garbage collection is not specified.
마찬가지로 가비지 컬렉션도 가비지 컬렉션의 타이밍이 지정되지 않았습니다.
Class loading is defined to be lazy, and class initialization is defined to be lazy.
클래스 로딩이 지연으로 정의되어 있고 클래스 초기화가 지연으로 정의되어 있습니다.
And so these things happen, these things just fall out of the natural semantics of class loading.
그래서 이런 일들이 일어나는데, 이런 일들은 클래스 로딩의 자연스러운 의미론에서 벗어나는 것입니다.
There are other optimizations that involve work shifting that we might like to do that
작업 이동을 수반하는 다른 최적화 방법도 있습니다.
might require some work by the user to enable or some specification changes to enable.
를 활성화하려면 사용자가 일부 작업을 수행하거나 사양을 변경해야 할 수 있습니다.
So for example, in the past we had an experimental AOT compiler which involves running a tool
예를 들어, 과거에는 도구를 실행하는 것과 관련된 실험적인 AOT 컴파일러가 있었습니다.
at build time saying compile those classes ahead of time.
빌드 시점에 해당 클래스를 미리 컴파일하라는 메시지를 표시합니다.
And similarly we have the class data sharing mechanism which involves caching information
그리고 마찬가지로 정보를 캐싱하는 클래스 데이터 공유 메커니즘이 있습니다.
from a training run to accelerate startup.
훈련 실행을 통해 시작을 가속화합니다.
And shifting work is fair game as long as the program's meaning is preserved.
그리고 프로그램의 의미가 유지되는 한 업무 이동은 공정한 게임입니다.
So Leiden will lean on what we're already doing with computation shifting by expanding
따라서 라이덴은 우리가 이미 연산 이동으로 하고 있는 것을 확장하여
the opportunities for computation shifting.
계산 이동의 기회를 확대할 것입니다.
So some kinds of shifting wouldn't require any spec changes at all.
따라서 어떤 종류의 이동은 사양 변경이 전혀 필요하지 않을 것입니다.
For example, like Lambda proxies are currently spun at runtime the first time you evaluate
예를 들어, 람다 프록시가 현재 런타임에 처음 평가할 때 회전하는 것처럼
a Lambda.
람다.
That's something that could be moved to build time with no specification change.
이는 사양 변경 없이 빌드 시간으로 이동할 수 있는 부분입니다.
Similarly, speculatively compiling code ahead of time.
마찬가지로, 추측적으로 코드를 미리 컴파일하는 것도 마찬가지입니다.
When I say speculatively, that means code would be willing to throw away if something
추측적으로 컴파일한다는 말은, 코드가 다음과 같은 경우 기꺼이 버릴 수 있다는 뜻입니다.
changed.
변경되었습니다.
There are other kinds of shifting that we might want to do that aren't allowed now,
지금은 허용되지 않는 다른 종류의 이동을 하고 싶을 수도 있습니다,
but we might extend the specification to allow it.
하지만 우리는 그것을 허용하도록 사양을 확장할 수 있습니다.
So for example, if you want to strip out code that you know is not going to be run
예를 들어, 실행되지 않을 것으로 예상되는 코드를 제거하려는 경우
or you promise is not going to be run.
또는 실행되지 않을 것이라고 약속한 코드를 제거할 수 있습니다.
Currently you're not allowed to do that because it could always be invoked reflectively.
현재는 항상 반사적으로 호출될 수 있기 때문에 그렇게 할 수 없습니다.
We would need to make some spec changes, which we may be willing to do, in order to support
다음을 지원하려면 몇 가지 사양을 변경해야 하는데, 기꺼이 그렇게 할 수 있습니다.
that kind of computation shifting.
그런 종류의 연산 이동을 지원합니다.
We may also investigate adding things to the programming model that allow you to talk about
프로그래밍 모델에 다음과 같이 이야기할 수 있는 것들을 추가하는 것도 검토할 수 있습니다.
constraints on the timing of computations.
계산 타이밍에 대한 제약 조건을 추가할 수도 있습니다.
So for example, maybe marking some static fields as lazy, which would mean you don't
예를 들어, 일부 정적 필드를 지연된 것으로 표시하면
have to do this immediately, you can do it later if you want.
이 작업을 즉시 수행하지 않아도 되고, 원한다면 나중에 수행할 수 있습니다.
Or maybe you can do it earlier if you want.
아니면 원한다면 더 일찍 할 수도 있습니다.
There's also an exploration going on called computed constants, which I'll talk about,
계산된 상수라는 탐색도 진행 중인데, 이에 대해 이야기하겠습니다,
which is a library-based programming model for shifting.
시프트를 위한 라이브러리 기반 프로그래밍 모델입니다.
So there's a lot of different options that we might want to pursue here.
따라서 여기서 추구할 수 있는 다양한 옵션이 있습니다.
Now some of the optimizations we might want to do might not be practical or safe without
이제 우리가 하고자 하는 최적화 중 일부는 다음과 같은 조건이 없으면 실용적이지 않거나 안전하지 않을 수 있습니다.
some additional permission from the user in the form of constraints like, I promise this
와 같은 제약 조건의 형태로 사용자의 추가 권한이 필요합니다.
won't happen.
는 일어나지 않습니다.
I promise this class will never be redefined.
이 클래스는 절대 재정의되지 않을 거라고 약속할게.
And some programs may be willing to accept those constraints.
그리고 일부 프로그램은 이러한 제약을 기꺼이 받아들일 수도 있습니다.
And they may be willing to accept quite a lot of constraints if there is sufficient
그리고 그들은 충분한 조건이 있다면 꽤 많은 제약을 기꺼이 받아들일 수도 있습니다.
benefit.
이익이 있다면.
So one of the key values of Project Leiden is that we want users to be in charge of choosing
따라서 프로젝트 라이덴의 핵심 가치 중 하나는 사용자가 직접 선택할 수 있도록 하는 것입니다.
which constraints they're willing to accept in order to get the benefits that they want.
원하는 혜택을 얻기 위해 어떤 제약을 기꺼이 받아들일지 결정하는 것입니다.
Because we know that different programs have different requirements and different goals
프로그램마다 요구 사항과 목표가 다르다는 것을 알고 있기 때문에
and different performance needs.
성능에 대한 요구사항도 다르기 때문입니다.
If you look at the extreme end of the spectrum, there's a somewhat severe constraint, which
스펙트럼의 극단적인 끝을 보면 다소 심각한 제약이 있습니다.
is the closed world assumption that the native image tool makes.
은 네이티브 이미지 도구의 닫힌 세계 가정입니다.
And this basically says, I promise there isn't going to be any dynamic class loading.
이것은 기본적으로 동적 클래스 로딩이 없을 것이라고 약속합니다.
I promise that I'm not going to do any reflection except for the list of methods I give you.
제가 알려드리는 메서드 목록 외에는 어떤 반성도 하지 않겠다고 약속드립니다.
And if you're willing to accept that constraint, then we can shift a great deal more computation
만약 당신이 그 제약을 기꺼이 받아들인다면, 우리는 훨씬 더 많은 계산을 옮길 수 있어요.
from runtime to compile time.
런타임에서 컴파일 타임으로 옮길 수 있습니다.
Not all applications are willing to live with such a constraint.
모든 애플리케이션이 이러한 제약을 감수할 수 있는 것은 아닙니다.
And so what we want to do is explore a broader range of constraints that may start with no
그래서 우리가 하고자 하는 것은 아니요로 시작할 수 있는 더 넓은 범위의 제약 조건을 탐색하는 것입니다.
constraints at all.
제약 조건이 전혀 없을 수도 있습니다.
And maybe we can give you something with no constraints.
어쩌면 제약 조건이 없는 것을 줄 수도 있습니다.
And then we can give you a little bit more with some constraints.
그리고 약간의 제약이 있는 것을 조금 더 줄 수 있습니다.
And then we can give you a lot more if you accept a lot of constraints.
그리고 많은 제약 조건을 받아들이면 더 많은 것을 줄 수 있습니다.
But the key is we want developers to be in charge of making these constraints and how
하지만 핵심은 개발자가 이러한 제약 조건을 만들고 그 제약 조건을 어떻게
willing they are to trade functionality for performance.
성능을 위해 기능을 희생할 의향이 있는지입니다.
So the sort of key concepts in this model are temporal shifting of computation, both
따라서 이 모델의 핵심 개념은 계산의 시간적 이동입니다.
forward and backwards.
앞뒤로 이동하는 것입니다.
Constraints on Java's dynamism as necessary to support the kinds of computation shifting
연산 이동의 종류를 지원하는 데 필요한 Java의 역동성에 대한 제약 조건
that a user may say, I'd like to get this benefit and I'm willing to consent to the
사용자가 이 혜택을 받고 싶다고 말할 수 있으며 기꺼이 동의합니다.
requirements.
요구 사항에 동의합니다.
We also want developers to be able to choose which optimizations they want and not, which
또한 개발자가 원하는 최적화와 그렇지 않은 최적화를 선택할 수 있기를 바랍니다.
constraints they're willing to accept and not.
제약 조건을 받아들일지 말지 선택할 수 있기를 바랍니다.
And this always has to preserve the meaning of the program.
그리고 이것은 항상 프로그램의 의미를 보존해야 합니다.
So these are the sort of ambitious goals of the project.
이것이 이 프로젝트의 야심찬 목표입니다.
So how are we going to achieve this?
그럼 어떻게 달성할 수 있을까요?
So a new concept that Leiden will introduce is a concept of a condenser.
그래서 라이덴이 도입할 새로운 개념은 콘덴서라는 개념입니다.
A condenser is a tool that runs at build time or package time or something like that, that
콘덴서는 빌드 시간이나 패키지 시간 또는 이와 유사한 시간에 실행되는 도구입니다.
takes a program image, performs some of the computation in that image, and creates a new
프로그램 이미지를 가져와서, 그 이미지에서 일부 연산을 수행한 다음, 새로운 이미지를 만듭니다.
program image that embodies the result of that computation.
프로그램 이미지를 새로 만듭니다.
That might be new code because we did some ahead of time compilation.
미리 컴파일을 했기 때문에 새로운 코드일 수 있습니다.
That might be new data.
새로운 데이터일 수 있습니다.
It might be new metadata like preloaded classes or pre-resolved call sites.
미리 로드된 클래스나 미리 확인된 호출 사이트와 같은 새로운 메타데이터일 수 있습니다.
It may be new constraints.
새로운 제약 조건일 수 있습니다.
The limitations on condensers is they have to be meaning preserving.
콘덴서에 대한 제약은 보존을 의미해야 한다는 것입니다.
They can't do arbitrary transformations of the semantics of the program.
프로그램의 의미를 임의로 변환할 수 없습니다.
The resulting image has to have the same meaning under the selected set of constraints.
결과 이미지는 선택된 제약 조건 하에서 동일한 의미를 가져야 합니다.
We want condensation to be composable, that you can feed the output of one condenser into
하나의 콘덴서의 출력을 다음에 공급할 수 있는 합성 가능한 콘덴서를 원합니다.
the input of another potentially multiple times if you have to.
다른 콘덴서의 입력을 잠재적으로 여러 번 공급할 수 있어야 합니다.
And we want the users to be in charge of selecting how to condense and when.
그리고 압축 방법과 시기는 사용자가 선택하도록 해야 합니다.
And like maybe if you're just doing testing or debugging, then you don't have to bother
테스트나 디버깅만 하는 경우라면 굳이
with any condensation.
응축이 있을 수 있습니다.
You can just run dynamically.
동적으로 실행할 수 있습니다.
And to the degree that shifting computation may require accepting constraints, the condenser
그리고 계산을 바꾸려면 제약 조건을 받아들여야 할 수도 있습니다.
configuration represents a certain set of tradeoffs between functionality and performance.
구성은 기능과 성능 사이의 특정 트레이드 오프 세트를 나타냅니다.
So we already do some of this in the JDK today.
그래서 우리는 이미 오늘날 JDK에서 이 중 일부를 수행하고 있습니다.
How many people here use AppCDS?
얼마나 많은 사람들이 AppCDS를 사용하나요?
How many people here know what AppCDS is?
AppCDS가 무엇인지 아는 사람이 몇 명인가요?
Okay, you guys are missing out on something here.
좋아, 너희들 뭔가 놓치고 있구나.
So this is a feature that's been in the JDK for two decades.
이 기능은 JDK에 20년 동안 있었던 기능입니다.
It started out as class data sharing, CDS, in the Java 5 timeframe.
이 기능은 Java 5에서 클래스 데이터 공유인 CDS로 시작되었습니다.
And it's basically a startup cache where it takes class file bytes for common system classes
그리고 기본적으로 공통 시스템 클래스에 대한 클래스 파일 바이트를 가져오는 시작 캐시입니다.
like string and integer and such that get loaded in every invocation and caches them
모든 호출에서 로드되는 문자열과 정수 같은 것들을 캐시에 저장합니다.
in a binary file that can be used to improve startup.
시작을 개선하는 데 사용할 수 있는 바이너리 파일에 저장합니다.
And because every invocation is going to load string and integer and security manager and
그리고 모든 호출이 문자열과 정수를 로드하고 보안 관리자와
the same usual suspects, a few hundred classes, this was a significant performance improvement.
수백 개의 클래스를 불러오기 때문에 성능이 크게 향상되었습니다.
But that's what CDS did 20 years ago.
하지만 20년 전 CDS가 했던 일입니다.
CDS has improved dramatically over time.
CDS는 시간이 지남에 따라 극적으로 개선되었습니다.
So in Java 8, it was enhanced to cache lab and proxy classes.
그래서 Java 8에서는 랩 및 프록시 클래스를 캐시하도록 개선되었습니다.
In Java 10, there was added tooling so that you could say, hey, cache these classes too.
Java 10에서는 이러한 클래스도 캐시할 수 있는 도구가 추가되었습니다.
Here are my application classes.
다음은 제 애플리케이션 클래스입니다.
I know we're going to get loaded at startup.
시작하면 부하가 걸릴 것 같아.
Just put them in the app CDS archive as well.
앱 CDS 아카이브에도 넣어주세요.
And then in Java 12, we added caching the module graph as well.
그리고 Java 12에서는 모듈 그래프 캐싱도 추가했습니다.
So this is a mechanism that stood us really well for a long period of time that has allowed
이 메커니즘은 오랜 기간 동안 우리를 정말 잘 버텨준 메커니즘입니다.
us to shift computation to build time to accelerate startup.
계산을 전환하여 시작을 가속화할 수 있는 시간을 확보할 수 있었습니다.
And so if this has been working so well, let's double down on that and let's use that for
이 방법이 잘 작동하고 있다면, 이 방법을 두 배로 늘려서
caching other things that can improve startup like profile data, like compiled code, like
프로파일 데이터, 컴파일된 코드와 같이 시작을 향상시킬 수 있는 다른 것들을 캐싱합니다.
linkage resolution for method invocations.
메서드 호출에 대한 연결 해결.
So the way app CDS works is there's an archive file, which is a big file containing cached
앱 CDS가 작동하는 방식은 아카이브 파일이 있고, 이 파일에는 캐시된 메소드가 포함된 큰 파일이 있습니다.
metadata.
메타데이터가 들어있는 큰 파일입니다.
It gets memory mapped at runtime and is used to accelerate today class loading and tomorrow
런타임에 메모리 매핑되어 오늘 클래스 로딩과 내일 로딩을 가속하는 데 사용됩니다.
more things.
더 많은 것들.
The JDK has a default archive, which is built when the JDK is built.
JDK에는 JDK를 빌드할 때 빌드되는 기본 아카이브가 있습니다.
That happens before you download the JDK.
JDK를 다운로드하기 전에 발생합니다.
It's when we actually build the JDK image.
실제로 JDK 이미지를 빌드할 때입니다.
And that will always get used unless you turn it off.
그리고 끄지 않는 한 항상 사용됩니다.
You can turn it off.
꺼도 됩니다.
And it contains metadata just on JDK classes.
그리고 JDK 클래스에만 메타데이터가 포함되어 있습니다.
But you can select with a command line switch a different archive file.
하지만 명령줄 스위치로 다른 아카이브 파일을 선택할 수 있습니다.
And you can create your own archive files and specify which classes to pre-process,
또한 직접 아카이브 파일을 생성하고 전처리할 클래스를 지정할 수도 있습니다,
which includes both JDK classes and your application classes.
여기에는 JDK 클래스와 애플리케이션 클래스가 모두 포함됩니다.
Now as the show of hands showed, most people aren't using this today.
손짓을 통해 알 수 있듯이 오늘날 대부분의 사람들은 이것을 사용하지 않습니다.
And they probably should because you can get a reasonable startup improvement for a very,
그리고 그들은 아마 그렇게 해야 할 것입니다. 왜냐하면 당신은 매우 합리적인 시작 개선을 얻을 수 있기 때문입니다,
very small amount of work.
아주 적은 양의 작업으로.
It's not going to work miracles.
기적이 일어나진 않을 거야.
But if it shaves 10%, 20%, 30% off startup, that may be enough for a lot of applications.
하지만 시작 시간을 10%, 20%, 30% 줄인다면 많은 애플리케이션에 적용하기에 충분할 수 있습니다.
So I'll give you a flavor for what these configuration flags look like.
이 구성 플래그가 어떻게 생겼는지 맛보기로 보여드리겠습니다.
They're not all that pretty.
그렇게 예쁘진 않네요.
So if you were going to use AppCDS today, you would perform one or more training runs,
오늘 AppCDS를 사용하려면 하나 이상의 트레이닝 실행을 수행해야 합니다,
like running a unit test or something like that, with a flag that says, dump out the
단위 테스트 등을 실행하는 것과 같은 작업을 수행해야 합니다.
classes that were loaded.
로드된 클래스를 덤프합니다.
And it'll dump them out to a file.
그리고 파일로 덤프합니다.
It's just a text file.
그냥 텍스트 파일입니다.
So you can edit it and merge them and whatever you want to do.
그러니 편집하고 병합하는 등 원하는 대로 할 수 있습니다.
And then there's another set of flags where you can say, take this list of classes and
그리고 또 다른 플래그 세트가 있는데, 이 클래스 목록을 가지고 다음과 같이 말할 수 있습니다.
create a AppCDS archive that caches the loading of those classes.
해당 클래스의 로딩을 캐시하는 AppCDS 아카이브를 생성합니다.
And then you distribute that archive with your program.
그리고 그 아카이브를 프로그램과 함께 배포합니다.
And your run script specifies that CDS archive when it goes to run your program and your
그리고 실행 스크립트에서 프로그램을 실행할 때 해당 CDS 아카이브를 지정하고
program gets faster.
프로그램이 더 빨라집니다.
So to give you an example of the orders of magnitude that you might see with this, so
이를 통해 볼 수 있는 크기의 순서를 예로 들어보면 다음과 같습니다.
Java C compiling one file, not a bad startup test, with CDS explicitly disabled on somebody's
CDS가 명시적으로 비활성화된 상태에서 시작 테스트가 아닌 하나의 파일을 컴파일하는 Java C의 경우
laptop, we got 300 milliseconds.
노트북에서 300밀리초가 걸렸습니다.
With the default CDS, we got 260 milliseconds.
기본 CDS를 사용하면 260밀리초입니다.
So that's like a 15% improvement, not so bad.
15% 정도 개선되었으니 나쁘지 않은 수준입니다.
With AppCDS that did a training run that included the Java C classes that got loaded during
425 동안 로드된 Java C 클래스를 포함하는 트레이닝 실행을 수행한 AppCDS를 사용했습니다.
compilation, we managed to knock 50% off the startup of the cold start alternative.
컴파일을 통해 콜드 스타트 대안의 시작 시간을 50% 단축할 수 있었습니다.
And so this doesn't necessarily get you everything you want, but it's something that you've been
이 방법으로 원하는 모든 것을 얻을 수 있는 것은 아니지만, 이 방법을 통해
able to do for a long time.
오랫동안 할 수 있는 일이죠.
And it gets you quite a lot for a relatively little work.
비교적 적은 양의 작업으로 많은 것을 얻을 수 있습니다.
So it may be that we take all of this and we turn it into a condenser as part of the
그래서 우리는 이 모든 것을 가져다가 응축기로 바꾸어
early work in Project Leiden.
프로젝트 라이덴의 초기 작업입니다.
Most all interesting techniques for startup improvement rely at some level on training
스타트업을 개선하기 위한 흥미로운 기술들은 대부분 어느 정도는 교육에 의존한다.
runs, which is to actually run some part of the program and observe what it did, observe
실행, 즉 실제로 프로그램의 일부를 실행하고 그것이 무엇을했는지 관찰하고 관찰하는 것입니다.
what classes it loads, observe what methods are hot, which is basically allowing us to
어떤 클래스를 로드하는지, 어떤 메서드가 핫한지 관찰하는 것입니다.
discover ahead of time what we would otherwise discover when we run the program dynamically.
프로그램을 동적으로 실행할 때 발견할 수 있는 것을 미리 발견할 수 있습니다.
So you write a small driver program, which you might be able to reuse an integration
따라서 통합을 재사용할 수 있는 작은 드라이버 프로그램을 작성합니다.
And as part of your build, you run the training run, it dumps some data out, and then you
그리고 빌드의 일부로 트레이닝 실행을 실행하고 일부 데이터를 덤프한 다음
do something with that data.
그 데이터로 뭔가를 하죠.
It's a very effective technique for the same reason dynamic compilation is effective, because
동적 컴파일이 효과적인 이유와 같은 이유로 매우 효과적인 기술입니다.
it allows us to base analysis and optimization on what does the program actually do, not
이 아니라 프로그램이 실제로 수행하는 작업을 기반으로 분석과 최적화를 수행할 수 있기 때문입니다.
just what does the program say.
프로그램이 무엇을 말하는지.
So as a kind of experiment in the last few months, we've been trying to identify what
그래서 지난 몇 달 동안 일종의 실험으로, 우리는 무엇을 확인하려고 노력해왔습니다.
can we do about startup at the least constraining end of the spectrum.
스펙트럼의 제약을 가장 적게 받으면서 시작할 수 있는 방법이 무엇인지 알아보고 있습니다.
Let's assume we're not willing to impose any new constraints, not change the spec, not
새로운 제약을 가하지 않고 사양을 변경하지 않는다고 가정해 봅시다.
sacrifice any dynamism, not give up on running any Java code.
역동성을 희생하지 않고, 자바 코드 실행을 포기하지 않습니다.
How far can we get?
얼마나 멀리 갈 수 있을까요?
So I have some experimental numbers that I'll show you, but first I want to talk a little
몇 가지 실험적인 수치를 보여드리겠습니다만, 그 전에 잠깐 이야기하고 싶습니다.
bit about how dynamic compilation actually works.
동적 컴파일이 실제로 어떻게 작동하는지에 대해 조금 설명하겠습니다.
So in the Hotspot JVM, there are a number of tiers used for compilation.
핫스팟 JVM에는 컴파일에 사용되는 여러 계층이 있습니다.
Tier 0 is the interpreter.
티어 0은 인터프리터입니다.
We have two compilers.
컴파일러가 두 개 있습니다.
C1 is a fast compiler that produces OK code, and then C2 or the GROL JIT are highly optimizing
C1은 OK 코드를 생성하는 빠른 컴파일러이고, C2 또는 GROL JIT는 고도로 최적화되어 있습니다.
compilers that produce awesome code, but they take longer to run.
컴파일러는 멋진 코드를 생성하지만 실행하는 데 시간이 오래 걸립니다.
So tier 0 is interpretation.
따라서 계층 0은 해석입니다.
Tiers 1 through 3 are various configurations of the C1 compiler, and tier 4 is using the
티어 1부터 3까지는 C1 컴파일러의 다양한 구성이고, 티어 4는
highly optimizing C2 or GROL JITs that benefit from profiling information gathered by running
를 실행하여 수집한 프로파일링 정보의 이점을 활용하는 고도로 최적화된 C2 또는 GROL JIT를 사용합니다.
in the interpreter or running C1 compiled code, but in general don't collect nearly
인터프리터에서 실행하거나 C1 컴파일된 코드를 실행하여 수집한 정보를 활용하지만, 일반적으로는 거의 수집하지 않습니다.
as much profile information.
만큼 많은 프로필 정보를 수집하지 않습니다.
So startup mostly happens in tier 0 through 3.
따라서 시작은 대부분 티어 0에서 3에서 발생합니다.
So we start with the interpreter, and then we graduate to C1, and then eventually we
그래서 우리는 통역사부터 시작해서 C1로 졸업하고, 결국에는 다음과 같이 됩니다.
figure out what code is hot, and we compile it with C2 or GROL.
어떤 코드가 핫한지 알아내서 C2나 GROL로 컴파일합니다.
And during that time, a lot of things like symbolic resolution, symbolic linkage, class
그리고 그 시간 동안 심볼릭 분해, 심볼릭 연결, 클래스
initializers get run.
이니셜라이저가 실행됩니다.
This all happens in the interpreter or in C1 usually.
이 모든 것은 인터프리터나 C1에서 보통 발생합니다.
Warm-up happens as the code we're running shifts from the lower tiers to the higher
실행 중인 코드가 하위 계층에서 상위 계층으로 이동하면서 워밍업이 발생합니다.
tiers.
티어.
We use the lower tiers to gather profiling information.
프로파일링 정보를 수집하기 위해 하위 계층을 사용합니다.
The JIT then uses that to make better optimizing decisions.
그런 다음 JIT는 이를 사용하여 더 나은 최적화 결정을 내립니다.
And the reason that we do this in a tiered fashion is if we gather profiling information
이 작업을 계층화된 방식으로 수행하는 이유는 프로파일링 정보를 수집하면 다음과 같습니다.
early, we can make better compilation decisions when we run the more expensive compiler.
더 비싼 컴파일러를 실행할 때 더 나은 컴파일 결정을 내릴 수 있기 때문입니다.
And peak performance is reached when all the hot code stabilizes in tier 4.
그리고 모든 핫 코드가 티어 4에서 안정화되면 최고 성능에 도달합니다.
JIT compilation is what we call speculative, which means the machine code that we generate,
JIT 컴파일은 우리가 생성하는 머신 코드를 의미하는 추측성 컴파일입니다,
we're always free to throw away.
우리는 언제나 자유롭게 버릴 수 있습니다.
And then we just bounce back to a lower tier.
그리고 더 낮은 계층으로 되돌아갑니다.
We go back to the interpreter.
다시 통역사로 돌아갑니다.
We go back to C1.
C1로 돌아갑니다.
And there are many reasons why we might deoptimize and go back to a lower tier.
최적화를 해제하고 더 낮은 계층으로 돌아가는 데는 여러 가지 이유가 있습니다.
Maybe there was an environmental change, like a new class got loaded that violated one of
다음 중 하나를 위반하는 새로운 클래스가 로드되는 등 환경 변화가 있었을 수도 있습니다.
our assumptions.
우리의 가정.
Maybe profiling data told us the code that we compiled before is no longer optimal.
프로파일링 데이터를 통해 이전에 컴파일한 코드가 더 이상 최적이 아니라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
Maybe we ran out of space in the code cache and had to make more room.
코드 캐시의 공간이 부족해서 더 많은 공간을 확보해야 할 수도 있습니다.
Maybe the user is using the debugger, and that caused some code to deoptimize.
사용자가 디버거를 사용 중이어서 일부 코드가 최적화되지 않았을 수 있습니다.
So JIT compilation, it's pure optimization.
그래서 JIT 컴파일은 순수한 최적화입니다.
It's one that we can freely do or undo.
우리가 자유롭게 실행하거나 취소할 수 있는 작업입니다.
So since we said, what can we do that doesn't involve any changes to the programming model
프로그래밍 모델을 변경하지 않고도 할 수 있는 일은 무엇일까요?
or to the code, we want to lean as heavily as we can on existing components in the VM,
like CDS and like our JITs.
CDS나 JIT처럼요.
And so what we did is basically taught CDS to gather additional information that is discovered
그래서 우리가 한 일은 기본적으로 CDS가 발견되는 추가 정보를 수집하도록 가르친 것입니다.
during a training run, like invocation profiles, like JIT compiled code, like class mirrors,
호출 프로파일, JIT 컴파일 코드, 클래스 미러와 같은 추가 정보를 수집하도록 학습시켰습니다,
like foo.class, resolved constant pool entries, resolved linkage states, pre-initialization
foo.class, 해결된 상수 풀 항목, 해결된 연결 상태, 사전 초기화 등
of some of the simplest classes.
가장 간단한 클래스 중 일부입니다.
And then when we go to load a class, or we can look in the CDS archive and say, do we
그리고 나서 클래스를 로드하거나 CDS 아카이브를 살펴볼 때 다음과 같이 말할 수 있습니다.
already have the metadata for this?
이미 메타데이터가 있나?
Great, we'll just reuse that.
좋아요, 그냥 재사용하면 되겠네요.
Do I have JIT code for it?
JIT 코드가 있나요?
Fantastic, I'll just use that.
멋지네요, 그냥 사용하겠습니다.
And so this is basically another big computation shifting trick where we cache profiles and
이것은 기본적으로 프로필을 캐싱하고, 프로필과
compiled code and linkage states from the training run and we reuse them in later runs.
트레이닝 실행에서 컴파일된 코드와 연결 상태를 캐시하고 이후 실행에서 재사용합니다.
And there's a lot of different ways to slice and dice this.
이를 잘게 쪼개서 분석하는 방법에는 여러 가지가 있습니다.
We could use this information not to cache JIT code, but to do better scheduling of compilation.
이 정보를 JIT 코드를 캐시하는 것이 아니라 컴파일 스케줄링을 개선하는 데 사용할 수 있습니다.
Or we could load JIT code from the archive.
아니면 아카이브에서 JIT 코드를 로드할 수도 있습니다.
And there's also tricks that we can do about, do we delay loading the code until all its
그리고 우리가 할 수 있는 트릭도 있는데, 코드를 모든
preconditions are met, like all the classes on which it depends is initialized?
전제 조건이 모두 충족될 때까지 로딩을 지연시킬 수 있을까요?
There's a lot of tricks that we can do with existing concepts in the runtime.
런타임에 기존 개념으로 할 수 있는 트릭이 많이 있습니다.
The cool thing about this is all of this is still speculative.
멋진 점은 이 모든 것이 아직 추측에 불과하다는 겁니다.
And so a cache profile or a cached code is a record of a dynamic observation of an application
따라서 캐시 프로파일 또는 캐시 코드는 애플리케이션의 동적 관찰에 대한 기록입니다.
from a previous run.
이전 실행에서
So we can use this information the same way, maybe with a little bit less confidence, as
따라서 이 정보를 동일한 방식으로, 아마도 조금 덜 신뢰하지만 다음과 같이 사용할 수 있습니다.
we do for profile information gathered in the current run.
현재 실행에서 수집한 프로필 정보에 대해 하는 것과 같은 방식으로 사용할 수 있습니다.
And if it turns out this doesn't work, if one of our assumptions is violated, we still
만약 이것이 작동하지 않거나 가정 중 하나가 위반되는 것으로 판명되면, 우리는 여전히
have the option to deoptimize, reprofile, reoptimize, et cetera.
최적화 해제, 재파일, 재최적화 등을 할 수 있는 옵션이 있습니다.
And so this is an approach that deals really well with surprises at runtime.
따라서 이 방법은 런타임에 발생하는 돌발 상황에 매우 잘 대처하는 접근 방식입니다.
Because things do change between training time and production, and we don't want the
훈련 시간과 프로덕션 시간 사이에 상황이 변하기 때문에, 우리는
application to fall over and break.
응용 프로그램이 넘어져서 깨지는 것을 원하지 않기 때문입니다.
We're more willing to say, all right, well, it just won't start up as fast if you change
변경하면 빨리 시작되지 않습니다.
something.
뭔가.
And this shouldn't be surprising, because this is stuff that Java has been good at for
이것은 놀라운 일이 아닙니다. 왜냐하면 이것은 자바가 오랫동안 잘 해왔던 것이기 때문입니다.
decades.
수십 년 동안 말이죠.
On the fly adaptation is one of Java's biggest strengths.
즉각적인 적응은 자바의 가장 큰 강점 중 하나입니다.
So there were 100 reasons why we might deoptimize.
비최적화를 해야 하는 이유는 100가지가 있습니다.
Something changed since training run is just one more of those reasons.
훈련 실행 이후 변경된 사항이 그 이유 중 하나에 불과합니다.
So some numbers.
몇 가지 숫자가 있습니다.
So we have the same ideal green curve, which is made up.
따라서 우리는 동일한 이상적인 녹색 곡선을 가지고 있습니다.
And we have the yellow curve, which is an observation of really running a program without
그리고 노란색 곡선이 있는데, 이는 실제로 프로그램을 실행하는 것을 관찰한 것입니다.
any of these tricks.
없이 실행했을 때의 관찰입니다.
And then we're going to add in this red curve, which is an observation of running the program
그리고 이 빨간색 곡선에 프로그램을 실행하는 동안 관찰한 결과를 추가하겠습니다.
with all these tricks that I just described.
방금 설명한 모든 트릭이 적용되었습니다.
And so for running Java C to compile 100 class files, we were able to see roughly
따라서 100개의 클래스 파일을 컴파일하기 위해 Java C를 실행하면 대략 다음과 같은 결과를 얻을 수 있습니다.
2x startup improvement and a pretty reasonable warm up improvement.
시작 시간이 2배 향상되고 워밍업 시간도 상당히 개선되었습니다.
We were able to bring down both the startup number and bring the yellow line down closer
시작 수치를 낮추고 노란색 선을 더 가깝게 만들 수 있었습니다.
to the green line for not very much work.
녹색 선에 가까워졌습니다.
We didn't have to change any code.
코드를 변경할 필요가 없었습니다.
We didn't have to give up any dynamism.
역동성을 포기할 필요가 없었습니다.
We just had to do a little bit more work at build time.
빌드 시간에 조금 더 많은 작업을 해야 했습니다.
So that's a pretty decent payoff for not very much work.
작업량이 많지 않은 것에 비하면 꽤 괜찮은 보상입니다.
And the numbers there represent not just one trick, but a lot of different tricks that
그리고 이 숫자는 한 가지 트릭이 아니라 다양한 트릭을 나타냅니다.
work together to give us a reasonable startup improvement for not that much work.
함께 작동하여 그다지 많은 작업을 하지 않고도 합리적인 시작 개선을 제공합니다.
Still early days.
아직 초기 단계입니다.
One of the things we spent a lot of time on is tuning VM policies, like compilation policies.
컴파일 정책과 같은 VM 정책을 조정하는 데 많은 시간을 할애했습니다.
And this is more of the same.
이것도 마찬가지입니다.
And so these are just pretty much rough numbers from the lab.
이 수치는 실험실에서 나온 대략적인 수치입니다.
Here's a kind of interesting one where we did the same thing with an XML validation
다음은 XML 유효성 검사로 동일한 작업을 수행한 흥미로운 결과입니다.
benchmark from SpecJVM.
벤치마크입니다.
And we didn't see any warm up improvement, but we did see like an 8x startup improvement,
워밍업 성능은 개선되지 않았지만 시작 성능은 약 8배 향상되었습니다,
which what this tells us is different workloads have different behaviors.
이는 워크로드에 따라 동작이 달라진다는 것을 의미합니다.
It's probably the case that there was a relatively small amount of code involved in this workload
아마도 이 워크로드에 관련된 코드의 양이 상대적으로 적기 때문일 것입니다.
that was identified to be hot relatively early, but there was a lot of work, setup work, that
비교적 일찍 뜨거워진 것으로 확인되었지만, 많은 작업, 설정 작업이 있었습니다.
we were able to shift at the beginning.
초반에 교대할 수 있었습니다.
And sometimes startup is the only interesting win, and that's fine, and we can take that.
때로는 시작이 유일하게 흥미로운 승리일 때도 있지만, 그건 괜찮아요, 우리는 받아들일 수 있어요.
All right.
알았어요.
The last example I want to give, and then we will wrap up, is Spring Boot Pet Clinic,
마지막으로 스프링 부트 펫 클리닉을 예로 들며 마무리하겠습니다,
which is sort of typical hello world plus plus spring application.
이것은 일종의 전형적인 헬로 월드 플러스 플러스 스프링 애플리케이션입니다.
And there's a few data points here.
그리고 여기에 몇 가지 데이터 포인트가 있습니다.
The first bar is startup time with just ordinary JDK 22, no tricks.
첫 번째 막대는 트릭이 없는 일반적인 JDK 22의 시작 시간입니다.
The yellow bar involves unpacking the application, which eliminates a lot of activity of loading
노란색 막대는 애플리케이션의 압축을 풀고 있는 상태로, 로딩 작업이 많이 제거된 상태입니다.
classes out of jars, which is something that people do all the time when they deploy these
클래스를 불러오는 작업을 제거하는데, 이는 사람들이 이러한 애플리케이션을 배포할 때 항상 하는 작업입니다.
applications anyway.
애플리케이션을 배포할 때 항상 하는 일입니다.
The next two bars, the light and dark blue, are various combinations of applying the improved
다음 두 막대인 하늘색과 진한 파란색은 개선된 기능을 적용한 다양한 조합입니다.
CDS that I just described of caching different things in the CDS archive.
방금 설명한 CDS 아카이브의 다양한 캐싱에 대해 설명했습니다.
And the last bar brings in the Spring AOT tools, which is basically like a condenser
그리고 마지막 바는 기본적으로 콘덴서와 같은 Spring AOT 도구를 가져옵니다.
that is spring specific, which basically does a training run, observes all of the annotation
기본적으로 트레이닝 실행을 수행하고 모든 주석을 관찰하는 스프링 전용입니다.
scanning and wiring of beans and all of that, and caches that in a faster to startup way.
스캔과 빈의 배선 등 모든 것을 관찰하고, 더 빠른 시작을 위해 캐시합니다.
And all of these different techniques synergize so that running more of these techniques gives
그리고 이 모든 다양한 기술이 시너지 효과를 발휘하여 이러한 기술을 더 많이 실행하면 다음과 같은 이점이 있습니다.
you a better result.
더 나은 결과를 얻을 수 있습니다.
And so what we saw was a roughly 4x startup improvement, again, not giving up anything,
그 결과 시작 속도가 약 4배 향상되었지만 아무것도 포기하지 않았습니다,
not giving up any dynamism, not changing any code.
역동성을 포기하지 않고 코드를 변경하지 않았습니다.
So there were a lot of things that fed into these numbers.
이 숫자에는 많은 것들이 영향을 미쳤습니다.
And there are more things that we're going to do in the future.
그리고 앞으로 더 많은 일들이 있을 겁니다.
Like I said, we're sort of just getting started here.
말씀드렸듯이, 이제 막 시작한 단계입니다.
But a lot of these tactics are additive.
하지만 이런 전술은 대부분 추가적입니다.
And so doing more of them together can give you a cumulatively better improvement.
따라서 여러 가지를 함께 사용하면 누적적으로 더 나은 결과를 얻을 수 있습니다.
So early class loading is a win.
따라서 클래스를 일찍 로딩하는 것이 승리입니다.
Cache and compiled code is a win.
캐시 및 컴파일된 코드가 승리입니다.
These are not surprising.
놀랍지 않습니다.
Resolving invoked dynamic call sites is a smaller win, but still a worthwhile one.
호출된 동적 호출 사이트를 해결하는 것은 더 작은 승리이지만 여전히 가치 있는 승리입니다.
The framework specific analysis that Spring does is really valuable because a big part
Spring이 수행하는 프레임워크별 분석은 정말 가치가 있습니다.
of what applications, like Spring applications do at startup, is annotation scanning.
Spring 애플리케이션과 같은 애플리케이션이 시작할 때 수행하는 작업의 상당 부분이 어노테이션 스캐닝이기 때문입니다.
And that involves a lot of relatively slow paths.
그리고 여기에는 상대적으로 느린 경로가 많이 포함됩니다.
And that can be observed through a training run and recorded.
그리고 그것은 훈련 달리기를 통해 관찰하고 기록할 수 있습니다.
But the upshot of this is that time shifting speculative optimization works pretty well.
결론은 시간 이동 투기적 최적화가 꽤 잘 작동한다는 것입니다.
It's a promising approach that gives us significant, although not as much of a gain as you would
여러분만큼의 이득은 아니지만 상당한 이득을 얻을 수 있는 유망한 접근법입니다.
see with something like Native Image, but not with all the constraints that Native Image
네이티브 이미지와 같은 것으로 볼 수 있지만, 네이티브 이미지가 가진 모든 제약이 있는 것은 아닙니다.
requires you to accept.
를 사용하려면 수락해야 합니다.
So you can get, with the giving up nothing end of the spectrum, you can get some decent
그래서 당신은 스펙트럼의 끝을 포기하지 않고도 괜찮은 것을 얻을 수 있습니다.
gains without giving up any compatibility or dynamism or changing your code.
호환성이나 역동성을 포기하거나 코드를 변경하지 않고도 상당한 이득을 얻을 수 있습니다.
And so what we've kind of done here is you can think of this work and Native Image as
따라서 이 작업과 네이티브 이미지를 다음과 같이 생각할 수 있습니다.
a pair of bookends.
한 쌍의 북엔드로 생각할 수 있습니다.
So at one end of the spectrum, we're saying, how much can I get giving up nothing?
스펙트럼의 한쪽 끝에서 우리는 아무것도 포기하지 않고 얼마를 얻을 수 있을까요?
At the other end of the spectrum, we're saying, how much can I get giving up a lot?
스펙트럼의 다른 쪽 끝에서 우리는 얼마나 많은 것을 포기할 수 있을까요?
And then there's a whole spectrum in the middle of, okay, can I give up some of those things
그리고 그 중간에는 전체 스펙트럼이 있습니다. 좋아, 내가 그런 것들 중 일부를 포기할 수 있을까?
and get some of the difference?
차액을 얻을 수 있을까요?
And we will continue to drill into the space in the middle as we move forward in this work.
그리고 우리는 이 작업을 진행하면서 중간에 있는 공간을 계속 뚫고 들어갈 것입니다.
So I just want to talk briefly about another exploration that's going on in Project Leiden,
프로젝트 라이덴에서 진행 중인 또 다른 탐사에 대해 간단히 이야기하고 싶습니다,
which is a library-based programming model exploration called computed constants.
계산된 상수라는 라이브러리 기반 프로그래밍 모델에 대한 탐구입니다.
And this is about shifting computation later in time.
그리고 이것은 계산을 나중에 옮기는 것에 관한 것입니다.
It's a mechanism for greater laziness without giving up the optimizations that you get from
최적화를 포기하지 않으면서도 더 많은 게으름을 피울 수 있는 메커니즘입니다.
static final fields.
정적 최종 필드.
And so the JVM already contains a known optimization for optimizing mutable static fields as if
따라서 JVM에는 이미 다음과 같이 변경 가능한 정적 필드를 최적화하는 알려진 최적화가 포함되어 있습니다.
if it knows that it will eventually converge to a stable value.
가 결국 안정적인 값으로 수렴할 것이라는 것을 알고 있다면 말입니다.
And it's sort of a dodgy kind of thing, and so it has not been made available as a general
그리고 그것은 일종의 회피적인 것이기 때문에 일반적으로 사용할 수 없습니다.
purpose optimization, but it's something that you see in the JDK code.
목적의 최적화가 아니라 JDK 코드에서 볼 수 있는 것입니다.
You see some code annotated with the internal annotation at stable.
내부 어노테이션으로 주석이 달린 코드가 안정적으로 표시됩니다.
And this is a hint to the JVM that says, once this is initialized, treat it as if it were
그리고 이것은 일단 이것이 초기화되면 마치
final.
So this is a really good example of that kind of static dynamic yin-yang.
이것은 정적 동적 음양의 좋은 예입니다.
It's a fully dynamic computation, but the VM is able to say, oh, well, if I look at
완전히 동적인 계산이지만, VM은 다음과 같이 말할 수 있습니다.
it through this lens, I can treat it as static.
이 렌즈를 통해 보면 정적인 것으로 취급할 수 있습니다.
And if I see somebody assigned to it, well, I know the assumption is violated and I can
그리고 만약 누군가가 거기에 할당된 것을 본다면, 저는 그 가정이 어긋난다는 것을 알고
deoptimize.
최적화 해제합니다.
So this is a cool optimization that we do internally, but was not ready for broad consumption,
이것은 내부적으로 수행한 멋진 최적화이지만 널리 사용할 준비가 되지 않았습니다,
which is why it's internal only.
그래서 내부 전용입니다.
So the computed constants exploration, which is still in the early phase, it's a draft
계산된 상수 탐색은 아직 초기 단계에 있으며, 초안입니다.
JEP for it, exposes that same optimization to user code.
사용자 코드에 동일한 최적화를 노출합니다.
And the way it works is you declare a computed constant and you give it a lambda to initialize
작동 방식은 계산된 상수를 선언하고 초기화할 람다를 제공하는 것입니다.
it.
And the first time anybody goes to read that computed constant, it goes and runs the initializer,
그리고 누군가가 이 계산된 상수를 처음 읽으려고 하면, 이 상수는 이니셜라이저를 실행합니다,
and thereafter caches it using at stable so that you get basically the full performance
그리고 그 이후에는 기본적으로 전체 성능을 얻을 수 있도록 안정적으로 캐시합니다.
of static final fields with the laziness of what looks like a dumb library for lazy initialization.
의 정적 최종 필드에 대해 게으른 초기화를 위한 멍청한 라이브러리처럼 보입니다.
It's not as dumb as it looks.
보기만큼 멍청하지 않습니다.
But what this lets us do is to say, identify individual calculations that say, this calculation
하지만 이를 통해 우리가 할 수 있는 것은 다음과 같은 개별 계산을 식별하는 것입니다.
doesn't need to be done so early, so I'm going to mark that as lazy, let it be shifted until
는 그렇게 일찍 수행될 필요가 없으므로, 이를 게으른 것으로 표시하고
it's needed without giving up any of the optimization benefits that we would ordinarily get from
로 이동시켜서 일반적으로 얻을 수 있는 최적화 이점을 포기하지 않고도 필요합니다.
static final fields.
정적 최종 필드.
And this mechanism may eventually be extended to talk about shifting earlier in time to
그리고 이 메커니즘은 결국 더 이른 시간으로 이동하는 것에 대해 이야기하기 위해 확장될 수 있습니다.
earlier phases of computation, but we're still early in the process of that.
초기 계산 단계로 확장할 수도 있지만, 아직은 초기 단계입니다.
So there's a lot of work left to do.
아직 해야 할 일이 많이 남았군요.
We have a prototype of condensers and a condenser toolkit.
콘덴서 프로토타입과 콘덴서 툴킷이 있습니다.
We have a lot more investigation about what other forms of computation can we shift and
우리는 어떤 다른 형태의 계산으로 전환할 수 있는지에 대해 더 많은 조사를 하고 있습니다.
what are the most interesting middle ground constraints that might allow us to do more
더 많은 일을 할 수 있는 가장 흥미로운 중간지대의 제약 조건은 무엇일까요?
shifting.
이동.
And I think the biggest challenge is finding the right way to bring shiftability into the
그리고 가장 큰 도전 과제는 시프터빌리티를
programming model so that the user is able to say, here's a computation that has certain
프로그래밍 모델에 적절한 방법을 찾는 것입니다.
semantic properties that the JVM can then identify as, oh, under these conditions, I
의미적 속성을 가진 연산이라고 말할 수 있습니다.
know I can shift that.
바꿀 수 있다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
So we're just getting started.
이제 시작이네요.
There's a lot left to do.
아직 할 일이 많이 남았어.
And I see my time is just about up, but I think we have time for a few questions.
시간이 거의 다 됐지만 몇 가지 질문할 시간이 있을 것 같아요.
So all right.
알았어요.
Any questions?
질문 있나?
So the question is, what can you use in production today?
그렇다면 오늘 프로덕션에서 무엇을 사용할 수 있을까요?
So all the work that I've described so far is highly experimental.
그래서 지금까지 설명한 모든 작업은 매우 실험적입니다.
And so if you want to use experimental code in production, well, you can do whatever you
따라서 프로덕션 환경에서 실험적인 코드를 사용하고 싶다면, 뭐든지 할 수 있습니다.
want.
하고 싶으면.
But it's not in a JDK anywhere yet.
하지만 아직 JDK 어디에도 없습니다.
What I expect you will start to see over the next couple of releases is some GEPs that
다음 몇 번의 릴리스에서 다음과 같은 GEP를 보게 될 것으로 예상됩니다.
describe smaller pieces like improvements to CDS.
CDS 개선과 같은 작은 부분을 설명합니다.
But what you can use in production today is AppCDS.
하지만 현재 프로덕션에서 사용할 수 있는 것은 AppCDS입니다.
And that is, like I said, it's been in the JDK for years and years.
앞서 말했듯이 이 기능은 수년 전부터 JDK에 존재해 왔습니다.
It has tooling for dumping and customizing CDS archives.
CDS 아카이브를 덤핑하고 커스터마이징하는 도구가 있습니다.
So that's not everything that I just described.
방금 설명한 것이 전부가 아닙니다.
But you can use that today.
하지만 오늘도 사용할 수 있습니다.
You can also use Native Image today if your application is suitable for the constraints
애플리케이션이 제약 조건에 적합하다면 지금 바로 네이티브 이미지를 사용할 수도 있습니다.
of Native Image.
의 네이티브 이미지입니다.
And I see you shaking your head.
네가 고개를 흔드는 게 보여.
So we understand not every workload is willing to accept those constraints.
모든 워크로드가 이러한 제약을 기꺼이 받아들이는 것은 아니라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
More questions?
질문이 더 있으신가요?
I can't see anything.
아무것도 안 보여요.
So there's a hand over here.
여기 손이 있네요.
OK, I'm sorry.
알았어, 미안해.
You talked about constraints.
제약 조건에 대해 얘기했잖아요.
What is the failure rule?
실패 규칙은 무엇인가요?
So if I accept a constraint and it turns out later, actually violated, what happens?
제약 조건을 수락했는데 나중에 실제로 위반한 것으로 밝혀지면 어떻게 되나요?
Yeah, that's a great question.
네, 좋은 질문이네요.
So the question is, let's say I opt into a constraint at build time.
문제는 빌드 시점에 제약 조건을 선택한다고 가정해 봅시다.
And then that constraint turns out to be violated.
그런데 그 제약 조건이 위반된 것으로 밝혀졌습니다.
What happens?
어떻게 될까요?
So I think it depends.
상황에 따라 다르겠지.
So for example, with at stable, you're making a sort of promise to the VM that says, this
예를 들어, 스테이블에서는 가상머신에 다음과 같은 일종의 약속을 하는 것입니다.
thing won't change after its value stabilizes.
값이 안정된 후에는 변경되지 않을 것이라고 약속하는 것입니다.
But the JVM doesn't believe you.
하지만 JVM은 당신을 믿지 않습니다.
So the optimization it does is speculative.
따라서 최적화는 추측에 불과합니다.
And if it sees you do a put field or put static to that field, it will say, oh, wait a second.
그리고 만약 당신이 풋 필드를 하거나 그 필드에 스태틱을 넣는 것을 본다면, "잠깐만요"라고 말할 것입니다.
Now I have to go and validate a whole bunch of code, which might be an expensive revocation.
이제 모든 코드의 유효성을 검사해야 하는데, 비용이 많이 들 수 있습니다.
So the consequence might be an expensive revocation, or the consequence might be an
그래서 그 결과는 비싼 취소일 수도 있고, 그 결과는
exception.
예외.
If you've said, I promise I'm not going to redefine this class ever, and then someone
이 클래스를 다시는 재정의하지 않겠다고 약속합니다.
tries to redefine that class, maybe you'll get an exception that says redefinition is
그 클래스를 재정의하려고 하면, 재정의는 다음과 같은 예외가 발생할 수 있습니다.
denied because this condenser configuration marked this class as non-redefinable.
이 콘덴서 구성이 이 클래스를 재정의할 수 없는 것으로 표시했기 때문에 거부되었습니다.
So I think it depends on whether there's a recovery possible or whether we just have
그래서 제 생각에는 복구가 가능한지 아니면 그냥
to say, you lied to me.
나한테 거짓말을 했어.
All right.
알았어.
I think, do I see a question right under the very bright lights over there?
저기 아주 밝은 불빛 아래에 질문이 보이나요?
Why was the field not final?
왜 필드가 마지막이 아니었나요?
Yes, because PowerPoint is a terrible IDE.
네, 파워포인트는 끔찍한 IDE이기 때문이죠.
So we're going to fix that right now.
그래서 지금 바로 고치겠습니다.
OK, public static final.
좋아, 공용 정적 파이널입니다.
OK, what were you talking about?
좋아, 무슨 소리야?
Yeah.
그래
So thank you, Mr. Compiler.
고마워요, 컴파일러 씨.
Any other questions?
다른 질문은 없나요?
Ah, yes, a question in the middle there.
아, 네, 중간에 질문이 있어요.
And I think that's probably the last question we have time for.
아마 이게 마지막 질문인 것 같아요.
So.
그럼.
So the question is, how is this related to crack?
그렇다면 이것이 크랙과 어떤 관련이 있을까요?
So they're related in the sense that they're exploring the same goal.
같은 목표를 탐구한다는 점에서 서로 연관되어 있습니다.
So project crack basically says, let's assume a checkpoint mechanism that's outside of the
그래서 프로젝트 크랙은 기본적으로 체크포인트 메커니즘이 다음과 같이 말합니다.
JDK, whether it be Criu or some cloud-based checkpoint mechanism.
JDK, 크리우든 클라우드 기반 체크포인트 메커니즘이든.
Let's run the application up to a certain point, freeze dry it, and then restore it.
애플리케이션을 특정 지점까지 실행하고 동결 건조시킨 다음 복원해 봅시다.
And then, well, that may not work because you may have done things like open socket.
그러면 오픈 소켓과 같은 작업을 수행했을 수 있으므로 작동하지 않을 수 있습니다.
So you have to register handlers for things that have to be redone at restore time.
따라서 복원 시점에 다시 실행해야 하는 작업에 대한 핸들러를 등록해야 합니다.
So I think crack is an interesting exploration.
그래서 크랙은 흥미로운 탐험이라고 생각합니다.
I'm not particularly optimistic about it because it is not something that allows you to
저는 특별히 낙관적이지 않아요. 왜냐하면 그것은 당신이 할 수 있는 것이 아니기 때문입니다.
validate that your program is correct through any sort of like sensible analysis.
어떤 종류의 합리적인 분석을 통해 프로그램이 올바른지 검증할 수 있는 것이 아니기 때문입니다.
You sort of have to debug your way into correctness by trying things and seeing what fails.
여러 가지를 시도하고 무엇이 실패하는지 확인하면서 올바른 방향으로 디버깅해야 합니다.
The problem with crack is that it's trying to interpret old code with new semantics
크랙의 문제는 오래된 코드를 새로운 의미로 해석하려고 한다는 것입니다.
and hope everything is good.
모든 것이 잘되기를 바랍니다.
And if it is good, great.
좋으면 좋죠.
It gives you great performance numbers.
훌륭한 성능 수치를 제공합니다.
If not, you just have broken code.
그렇지 않다면 코드가 깨진 것입니다.
And maybe if you're lucky, you get an exception.
운이 좋으면 예외가 발생할 수도 있습니다.
But maybe if you're unlucky, you just get wrong answers.
하지만 운이 나쁘면 오답을 얻을 수도 있습니다.
And those wrong answers come from assumptions that are violated deep in libraries that you
그리고 그 오답은 라이브러리 깊숙이 자리 잡은 잘못된 가정에서 비롯됩니다.
didn't even know were part of your application.
응용 프로그램의 일부인지도 몰랐던 가정에서 비롯됩니다.
So I think crack is a good exploration.
그래서 크랙은 좋은 탐험이라고 생각해요.
I think it's a, you know, but I'm not optimistic about it as a programming model.
알다시피 프로그래밍 모델로는 낙관적이지 않다고 생각해요.
I would much rather give people a programming model where if they, you know, whatever code
저는 차라리 사람들이 어떤 코드를 작성하더라도
that they have will run correctly 100% of the time.
를 입력하면 100% 올바르게 실행되는 프로그래밍 모델을 제공하고 싶습니다.
And then if they do some more work, they can make it run faster.
그리고 더 많은 작업을 수행하면 더 빠르게 실행할 수 있습니다.
Crack tries to make things run faster potentially at the expense of correctness.
크랙은 정확성을 희생해서라도 더 빠르게 실행하려고 합니다.
And I don't like that tradeoff.
그리고 나는 그 트레이드오프가 마음에 들지 않는다.
But I think it's an interesting exploration.
하지만 흥미로운 탐험이라고 생각해요.
I'm glad it's going on.
진행 중이라 다행이네요.
But I wouldn't bet on that direction.
하지만 그 방향에 내기를 걸진 않겠어.
So all right.
알았어.
Thank you very much, everyone.
모두들 수고했어요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.